Andrew Jackson Davis Collection
The Edgar Cayce Foundation
Andrew Jackson Davis Collection
1840 2011
Coll. 2
The Edgar Cayce Foundation
1.2 Linear Feet
Davis, Andrew Jackson
Davis, Delphine Markham
Atherton, Frederick
Arrangement
Andrew Jackson Davis's materials are followed by Delphine Markham Davis's materials in the collection arrangement.
Custodial History
The Association for Research and Enlightenment Library acquired the collection in 1977 from Maude Kline, friend of Edgar Cayce. The collection of books that accompanies this manuscript collection is housed in the A.R.E. Library.
Andrew Jackson Davis's lawyer Frederick Atherton originally owned the collection. After Atherton's death, it passed to a Mrs. McCullem who willed the collection to Maude Kline. (see A.R.E. News, vol. 13 no. 3, March 1978).
Fred Kolb, member of the A.R.E. Board of Trustees, Dr. John Bullard and Dr. Craig McAndrews advised the Library on the purchase.
Related Materials
Andrew Jackson Davis collection of publications located in the A.R.E. Library reserve room and available for research upon request and appointment.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes artifacts, correspondence, legal records, photographs, and writings primarily related to Davis's publishing contracts. Letters between Davis and his lawyer Frederick Atherton form the bulk of the correspondence. In addition, the collection includes personal papers of Davis' wife, Delphine Markham Davis (1839-1928). Delphine, a graduate of the United States Medical College in New York, married Davis in 1885.
Biographical / Historical
Andrew Jackson Davis was born August 11, 1826 in Blooming Grove, New York. After a series of psychic experiences, he moved to Poughkeepsie, New York and became an ardent Spiritualist known popularly as "The Poughkeepsie Seer." Davis was a prolific writer and lecturer on Spiritualist and socially progressive topics. He served briefly as editor of the Banner of Light, a Spiritualist newspaper based in New England. In 1843, Davis attended a lecture on mesmerism given by Dr. Dr. J. S. Grimes, professor of jurisprudence in the Castleton Medical College. Soon after the lecture, a local tailor named William Livingston guided Davis into a trance state, where he discovered he could see the inside of the human body and diagnose illness. According to the Encyclopedia of Occultism and Parapsychology, "In 1844 Davis had a strange experience that was to have an enduring effect on his life. In a state of semitrance he wandered away from home and awoke the next morning 40 miles away in the mountains. There he claimed to have met two venerable men - whom he later identified as the ancient physician Galen and the Swedish seer Emmanuel Swedenborg - and experienced a state of mental illumination" (https://www.encyclopedia.com/people/philosophy-and-religion/other-religious-beliefs-biographies/andrew-jackson-davis). In 1845, he partnered with Dr. Silas Lyon and the Reverend William Fishbough to explore his abilities on a deeper level. Lyon guided his trance state and Fishbough recorded the sessions. From November of 1845 to February of 1847 they gathered the material that would become The Principles of Nature, Her Divine Revelations, and a Voice to Mankind (1847). Through the following years Davis would publish several other works on Spiritualism and philosophy. In 1860 he started the Herald of Progress magazine. He later ran a small bookshop in Boston and earned a medical degree. He was an important influence in the development of Spiritualism as well as a supporter of progressive political movements such as divorce reform. Davis died on January 13, 1910.
- Box 1
  - accession materials, 1977 2011; Folder 1:1
  - correspondence, [personal], 1909 1937; Folder 1:2
  - correspondence, [Frederick Atherton to James Robertson], 1911 1912; Folder 1:3
  - annuity, [Massachusetts Hospital Life Insurance Company], 1899 1902; Folder 1:4
  - bill of sale, [Trow Directory, Printing and Bookbinding Company], 1890 1910; Folder 1:5
  - biographical sketches, [Andrew Jackson Davis] by Delphine Davis et. al., 1886 1909; Folder 1:6
  - Certificate of Incorporation of the Harmonial Association, 1881; Folder 1:7
  - charter, [The Magazine Company], 1906; Folder 1:8
  - correspondence, [American Society for Psychical Research], 1908; Folder 1:9
  - correspondence, [Frederick Atherton], 1905 1910; Folder 1:10-1:14
  - correspondence, [Austin Publishing Company], 1908 1910; Folder 1:15
  - correspondence, [Banner of Light Publishing Company], 1905 1908; Folder 1:16
  - correspondence, [British Spiritualist lyceums], 1898; Folder 1:17
  - correspondence, [William Fishbough], 1847 1854; Folder 1:18
  - correspondence, [Alfred E. Giles], 1884 1902; Folder 1:19
  - correspondence, [Reverend T.L. Harris], 1847 1848; Folder 1:20
  - correspondence, [legal], 1909; Folder 1:21
  - correspondence, [Ella Mingus], 1886; Folder 1:22
  - correspondence, [National Association of Spiritualists], 1902 1909; Folder 1:23
  - correspondence, [J.M. Peebles], 1905; Folder 1:24
  - correspondence, [C.M. Plumb], 1888; Folder 1:25
  - correspondence, [The Progressive Thinker], 1905 1923; Folder 1:26
  - correspondence, [readers], 1905 1906; Folder 1:27
  - correspondence, [John T. Townsend], 1884 1885; Folder 1:28
- Box 2
  - correspondence, [Trow Directory, Printing and Bookbinding Company, 1894 1909; Folder 2:1-2:2
  - correspondence, [Veteran Spiritualist's Union], 1896 1908; Folder 2:3
  - divorce petition, [Catherine De Wolf v. Joshua Dodge], 1848; Folder 2:4
  - ephemera, 1903 1909; Folder 2:5
  - accession materials, 1903 1909; Folder 1:1
  - legal agreement, [George C. Webster and Lyman W. Griffin, pharmacists], 1893; Folder 2:6
  - legal documents, [Samuel S. Love v. Mary F. Davis alias Mary F. Love], 1856; Folder 2:7
  - legal documents, [probate], 1910 1912; Folder 2:8
  - legal documents, [probate; James De Wolf], 1859; Folder 2:9
  - legal documents, [Christopher C. Shaw et. al. v. Veteran Spiritualist's Union et. al.], 1906 1909; Folder 2:10
  - judgment, [Andrew Jackson Davis v. Mary F. Davis / Love / Robinson], 1885; Folder 2:11
  - manuscript, [An Explanatory Letter from Andrew Jackson Davis to His Correspondents Who Complain That They Do Not Receive His Books From the Publishers], 1905; Folder 2:12
  - marriage contract, [Andrew Jackson Davis and Catherine De Wolf], 1848; Folder 2:13
  - marriage contract, [Andrew Jackson Davis and Delphine E. Markham], 1885; Folder 2:14
  - medical license, 1883; Folder 2:15
  - notes, [books and lectures], 1879 1884; Folder 2:16
  - paintings, [subjects from Davis' writings], undated; Folder 2:17
  - pamphlet, [The Diakka, and their Earthly Victims; being an Explanation of much that is False and Repulsive in Spiritualism], 1873; Folder 2:18
  - pamphlets, [Harmonial Association and Philosophy], 1872 1907; Folder 2:19
  - pamphlets, [lyceums], undated; Folder 2:20
  - pamphlets, [medical remedies], 1893 1895; Folder 2:21
  - pamphlets, [Spiritualism], 1905; Folder 2:22
  - photographs, 1840 1910; Folder 2:23-2:24
  - poem, undated; Folder 2:25
  - publications, [Andrew Jackson Davis memorials], 1910; Folder 2:26
  - receipts, [Ella Mingus], 1885 1887; Folder 2:27
  - receipts, [publishers], 1895 1904; Folder 2:28
  - receipts, [Eliza P. Williams], 1884 1887; Folder 2:29
- Box 3
  - account books, 1913 1927; Folder 3:1
  - Andrew Jackson Davis Publication Trust, 1922 1923; Folder 3:2
  - correspondence, [Frederick Atherton], 1910 1923; Folder 3:3-3:4
  - correspondence, [mourning], 1910; Folder 3:5
  - correspondence, [personal], 1914 1928; Folder 3:6
  - correspondence, [Winthrop Scudder and family], 1927 1928; Folder 3:7
  - ephemera, 1882 1928; Folder 3:8
  - legal documents, [divorce], 1869 1885; Folder 3:9
  - legal documents, [property], 1869 1892; Folder 3:10
  - marriage contract, [Delphine Markham and Dumont C. Dake], 1870
  - newsclippings, [Spiritualist newspapers] collected by Delphine Davis, undated
  - photographs, [Delphine Davis], undated; Folder 3:14
  - receipts, 1927 1928; Folder 3:15
  - wills, 1910 1922; Folder 3:16
- Box 4
  - staff, undated; Item 4:1
- Box 5
  - medal, [British Spiritualists' Lyceum Union], 1863; Item 5:1
  - medal, [British Spiritualists' Lyceum Union], 1863; Item 5:2
  - ambrotype, [Andrew Jackson Davis], undated; Item 5:3
  - sash, undated; Item 5:4
  - medal, [depiction of the Rochester Rappings], undated; Item 5:5
- Box 6
  - ledger, 1874 1887; Item 6:1